Guide to the Devereux Family papers, 1791-1936 and undated RL.10046
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Devereux Family papers
1776-1936 and undated, bulk 1839-1900
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Devereux family
RL.10046
3 Linear Feet
The Devereux family lived in Raleigh, N.C. They were a prominent and wealthy family before the Civil War. This collection is largely concerned with personal and family affairs; the chief correspondents in the collection are Thomas Pollock Devereux (1793-1869), his sister-in-law Sarah Elizabeth Devereux, his son John Devereux (1819-1893), daughter-in-law Margaret (Mordecai) Devereux (1824-1910), and Robert L. Maitland of New York, a business associate. Subjects covered by the letters include camp life in the Civil War, plantations, slaves and real estate.
Biographical note
The Devereux family lived in Raleigh, N.C. They were a prominent and wealthy family before the civil war.
Collection Overview
This collection is largely concerned with personal and family affairs. The chief correspondents in the collection are Thomas Pollock Devereux (1793-1869), his sister-in-law Sarah Elizabeth Devereux, his son John Devereux (1819-1893), daughter-in-law Margaret (Mordecai) Devereux (1824-1910), and Robert L. Maitland of New York, a business associate. A few letters relate to the Civil War careers of John Devereux, chief quartermaster of North Carolina, and his son, Thomas Pollock Devereux, and describe camp life.
Postwar papers concern land sales, lawsuits over estates, and involvement in the French spoliation claims. There are also comments on slaves and manumission, Dare County, lumbering, the Lane and Mordecai families, cranberry culture, and land surveys. There are financial and legal papers, writings of Margaret Devereux, clippings, and genealogical material; a family reminiscence by Margaret Devereux; a recipe book; a composition book of Annie Lane Devereux; a personal and professional ledger, 1821-1839, of Thomas Pollock Devereux; and a plantation account book, 1842-1863, of John Devereux, relating to Barrow, Montrose, and Runiroi plantations and giving extensive lists of slaves with names, dates of birth, purchase, or death; and other notations.
Provenance
The Devereux Family papers were purchased by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1972.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Roanoke River (Va. and N.C.); Slavery -- North Carolina; Slave records -- North Carolina; Real property -- North Carolina; Plantations -- Records; Plantations -- North Carolina; Devereux family; Mordecai family; Maitland, Robert L.; Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life; Devereux, Thomas Pollock; Devereux, Sarah Elizabeth; Confederate States of America. Army -- Officers; Lane family; Devereux, Margaret Mordecai; Devereux, John
- Devereux Family papers, 1791-1936 and undated; 1
  - Information folder (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1857-1858 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1856 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1846-1849 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1842-1845 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1791-1841 (Box 1)
  - Genealogy (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1885-1936 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1869 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1873 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Obituaries), 1884-1922 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany (Box 2)
  - Financial papers, 1850s (Box 2)
  - Financial papers, 1860-1876, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Financial papers, 1840s (Box 2)
  - Legal papers, 1776 (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1839-1865, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Legal papers, 1842-1876 (Box 2)
  - Legal papers, 1894-1910 (Box 2)
  - John Devereux Plantation Account book, 1842-1863 (Box 3)
  - Recipes: Mrs. J. Devereux (Box 3)
  - Annie Lane Devereux Composition Book (Box 3)
  - Thomas Pollock Devereux Personal Ledger, 1821-1839 (Box 3)
  - Account book, circa 1860 (Box 3)